

I am a Senior Enterprise Security Architect, Organizational Leader and Computer Scientist with 32 years of experience building systems and leading teams and projects. I specialize in the areas of Computer Security, Cloud Computing and Configuration Management. I have experience working with and leading remote teams. I possess a strong combination of leadership, conceptual and technical skills with excellent communication abilities.

Key skills ____

Leadership 32 years of team and project leadership experience; IT Enterprise Architecture.

Computer Security Enterprise security architecture; virtualization and cloud computing security; risk man-

agement and compliance; intrusion detection and prevention; software security and se-

cure software development.

Cloud Computing AWS architecture, infrastructure, development and security.

Communications and Research Excellent written and spoken communication skills; research and teaching experience.

Research Ph.D. in Computer Science, 9 years of experience at IBM Research.

Languages Spanish (native), English (100%), German (B1 level).

Experience _____

Amazon Web Services

2021 – Present

Switzerland

SENIOR GLOBAL SECURITY ARCHITECT

Oct 2021 – Present

- I work with customers and within AWS to increase security awareness, design and build secure solutions, mentor and develop colleagues and customers in security best practices.
- As Lead Security Architect at the Stellantis Virtual Engineering Workbench (VEW) project, I have:
 - Established the VEW security workstream, define and promote security best practices and drive activities related to risk analysis, threat modeling and mitigation.
 - Established measurement mechanisms for status and metrics for security activities, which provide visibility to both technical and business stakeholders.
 - Established a Security Champions program to promote and transfer security knowledge.
 - Define and track security features to fulfill customer business requirements and AWS best practices.

GLOBAL SECURITY ARCHITECT Sep 2021 – Sep 2021

- Worked with AWS global customers to improve security posture and promote secure design and implementation practices.
- In the Volkswagen Digital Production Platform (DPP) program, I established scalable and durable mechanisms to enable DPP partners to work securely in the DPP program. I also created and promoted security learning materials tailored for various roles within the project, and increased security awareness and knowledge by promoting a Security Guardians initiative across the organization.

Swisscom 2014 – 2021 Switzerland/U.S.A.

ENTERPRISE ARCHITECT AND IT CLOUDS SOLUTION SECURITY ARCHITECT

Apr 2019 – Sep 2019

- As a Solution Security Architect for IT Clouds, I was a member of the Swisscom IT Clouds leadership team:
 - I defined and manage yearly KPIs and the security features and characteristics of Swisscom's cloud offerings.
 - I ensured cloud platform and service compliance with internal, contractual and regulatory standards (e.g. ISO27001, ISAE3402/3000, FINMA and GDPR).
 - I established and manage the Security Champions initiative to promote and improve a culture of security responsibility.
 - I established organization-wide processes for risk management, threat modeling, audits and penetration testing.
 - I was the point of contact for CISO-level interactions with Swisscom's cloud customers.
- As an Enterprise Architect, I defined future Swisscom products and solutions as part of the Swisscom Enterprise Architecture team.

APRIL 29, 2023 DIEGO ZAMBONI

- Starting as a project lead and architect, I founded and led a team of up to 16 people that designed, implemented and operated the monitoring and logging capabilities for Swisscom's IaaS and PaaS evolving cloud offerings:
 - Unified diverse monitoring components into a cohesive framework, reducing costs and increasing efficiency by 20%.
 - Defined architecture and implemented customer-facing monitoring and logging services.
 - Designed and implemented the Orchard monitoring platform for Swisscom's Application Cloud.
 - Defined and implemented integrations between Jira and OpsGenie for alerting of user-reported incidents.
 - Managed business relationship and implemented Swisscom-wide use of OpsGenie for alert management.
 - Managed engineering relationship with VMware for integration of their products in Swisscom's monitoring systems.

CFEngine AS

2011 – 2014 Norway/U.S.A. (remote)

SENIOR SECURITY ADVISOR AND PRODUCT MANAGER

Oct 2011 – Jun 2014

- Developed the CFEngine language roadmap and security strategy.
- Acted as overall CFEngine Advocate, with a special focus on security.
- Published the book Learning CFEngine (O'Reilly Media), which was used for promotion and education.
- Established and led the CFEngine Design Center project through its initial implementation phase.

HP Enterprise Services

2009 - 2011

Mexico

ACCOUNT SECURITY OFFICER AND SERVICE DELIVERY CONSULTANT

Nov 2009 - Oct 2011

- Managed security-related topics for HP enterprise customers in Mexico and abroad.
- · Managed all security-related aspects of the design, implementation and delivery of IT Outsourcing projects.
- Analyzed, designed and implemented solutions in the areas of system automation, configuration management, system administration, system design, virtualization, performance and security.

IBM Zurich Research Lab

2001 - 2009

Switzerland

RESEARCH STAFF MEMBER

Oct 2001 – Oct 2009

- Established and developed research projects in intrusion detection, malware containment, and virtualization security, including:
 - Project Phantom: Security for VMware virtual environments using virtual machine introspection.
 - Billy Goat: An active worm-detection and capture system, deployed in the IBM internal and external networks.
 - Router-based Billy Goat: An active worm-capture device deployed at the network boundary and coupled with a border router to effectively and automatically spoof every unused IP address outside the local network.

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM)

1991 - 1996

Mexico

HEAD OF COMPUTER SECURITY AREA AND SYSTEM ADMINISTRATOR

Nov 1991 – Aug 1996

- Established UNAM's first Intrusion Response Team, which has since evolved into a much larger organization.
- Managed security services for the supercomputing organization and for the whole University, including incident response, security information, auditing and teaching.
- Established the *International Computer Security Day*, which has grown and divided into the *Computer Security Day* (a one-day event) and the *Seguridad en Cómputo* (Computer Security) conference (a multi-day event).
- System Administrator at UNAM's Supercomputing Center, managing UNAM's Cray Y-MP Supercomputer and related systems.

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, U.S.A. 1996-2001

 ${\it Using Internal Sensors for Computer Intrusion Detection}, {\it Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.}$

Certifications



















Research, Publications, Teaching and References $_$

Books: Learning CFEngine (2012), Learning Hammerspoon (2018), Literate Configuration (2019), Publishing with Emacs, Org-mode and Leanpub (2021).

References available upon request. Full Curriculum Vitæ available at https://zzamboni.org/vita/.

April 29, 2023 Diego Zamboni